Hey there, welcome to the Posit Data Science Hangout. I'm Libby Herron, and this is a recording
of our weekly community call that happens every Thursday at 12pm US Eastern Time. If
you are not joining us live, you miss out on the amazing chat that's going on. So find
the link in the description where you can add our call to your calendar and come hang
out with the most supportive, friendly, and funny data community you'll ever experience.
Can't wait to see you there. And speaking of people who make impact, I would really
like to introduce you to our featured leader today, Vytas Vaiciulis. He is Lead Data Scientist
at CSO, which is Central Statistics Office Ireland. Vytas, thank you so much for joining
us today. And I would love it if you could introduce yourself, tell us a little bit about
what you do at CSO, and then also something that you like to do for fun.
Thank you very much. So very happy to be here. So I'm originally from Lithuania, but I've
been living in Ireland for more than 30 years. And what do you do at CSO? So I lead a section
on analytics and AI innovations, which I'm very proud to say, when I began working in
that section, it was team of one, and now it's team of 13. So I build it from the ground
up, and the entire idea of the section was to modernize our statistics, which I have
done, and I'm very proud of it. And that's where my interaction with POSIT comes in,
and our studio. So that's kind of like my professional work. For fun, I have access
to the Atlantic Ocean. So I go for swims in the Atlantic Oceans, and in my spare time,
I lift heavy objects, and I put them back down. That keeps me sane, because it frees
up the mind from my day-to-day thinking, because in data science, there's a lot of thinking,
so sometimes I want to forget a little bit, and de-stress.
I don't think you're the only lifter here. I used to lift too. You're in good company.
All right, everybody, get your questions for Vitus ready. Isabella is going to share Slido
links again in the chat so that you know where to ask questions. But I would like to
ask you, Vitus, how did you get to Ireland? How did you get to CSL?
So I suppose, initially, it was my family. So when I was 13 years old, my parents moved
to Ireland. And when I was in Lithuania one of the days, they rang me up and said, son,
we're moving to Ireland. I was, OK. So that's how I initially moved to Ireland. Long story
short, after that, I did all of my education in Ireland. I went to school, which was a very
new experience. And then after I finished up my university, I was applying for jobs.
And by pure chance, I ended up in CSO, Central Statistics Office. And I've been always working
here, because I always wanted to work with data. It's funny how life works out, because one of the
days I was in Lithuania, I was walking around, and I saw Lithuanian Central Statistics Office.
I was like, I would like to work for this. And chances happen, I end up working for Ireland's
statistical office. But I keep close relationships with Lithuanian statistical office as well.
Amazing. Is statistics, straight statistics, your background? How did you get here education-wise?
So actually, my education is quite different. My dream was to get into programming. So that's
what I actually studied in the university. I studied computers, and my background was programming.
And then when I did master's, I did it in data analytics and machine learning. That's how I
developed real passion for AI, as I told people way, way back then when AI wasn't popular.
So now when actually AI became popular, I must say, I got on that train right away,
because that was my passion all along. It just was sleeping there. The moment wasn't quite right.
So yeah, so that's how I began working with data. That's my background.
And I suppose that's the area where I always wanted to be in.
Well, I'm glad that you got there. Could you tell us a little bit about what CSO does, and give an
example of the types of data that you work with and see on a daily or weekly basis, just so that
we can have a good sort of understanding? Because we come from all different backgrounds, whether
that's biology, working with assay data, or maybe we come from financial institutions where everything
is transactional. But I think that you see a very specific type of data, or a few types of data.
Yeah, to be honest, I think it's a very good question, because sometimes, you know, we forget
an area that we're in. So just to give a little bit of context, CSO is a central statistics office
for the Irish government. And every government in the world, they have the same, they have a central
statistics office. So what we do, we do public releases on various things, like how many people
live in the country, which you might know is census. And then we do lots of important economic
things like CPI, GDP, things along those lines. And if you combine all the releases together,
CSO as an organization does around 300 releases a year. So on various, various different
things. And the way we get our data for those releases historically has been surveys. So
somebody knocks on your door and asks you to complete a survey. That's historically how we
get the data in. Now, in the recent times, all statistical offices around the world,
they see that people no longer like to answer doors. It's a different area that we live in. So
statistics are changing a little bit, but I guess alternative is there. So statistical offices are
now moving more to administrative data sources, basically data that does not come directly from
the people. Surveys are still there. There's still like a lot of man in the service that you
need to do, but unfortunately the responses, response rates are dropping down. People are
just not responding. So as I say, other data sources are coming in. So we'll work closely
with other governmental departments, with LinkedIn, with all the governmental agencies,
and we get data from them, which is transactional level data. In some cases, it's no longer
a survey when you have complete data sets. So in some cases, it's very good. And we also see
some very interesting sections set up. I even see in my organizations, geospatial data.
That's very new. So like in some cases, we have some mandatory statistics that we need to produce for
sustainable development goals. And one of them is CO2 emissions. Now, question is, how do you
measure CO2 emissions? You can't ask a person, what's your CO2 emission in your backyard?
Satellite. Satellite sees that. So I suppose satellite will be one of the most advanced data
sources, but just to say the variety of data sources that are coming in moved way beyond
just knocking on the doors and asking for people's information to all these diverse
data sources, other governmental departments, satellite,
data, and many others. So I suppose like that is how we work now.
Okay. Well, we have a fantastic question to get us started in Slido, and it's from Anna.
I think that we can have Anna unmute and ask her question live. Let's see if that's possible.
Maybe. Sorry, I'm so dazed. And I hope I did it right.
Yeah, if you don't mind, I'll stay off the video.
My question is, what programming languages do you use in your work? And was that the same
language that you study in school? Very good question. That comes very
close at heart. No, when I was in school, I developed a passion for Java. I really liked
that. But to be honest, it set me up for life because I really liked the object-oriented
way of thinking. But then in practice, once I moved into office, Java wasn't really used.
Now, in our office, our legacy language for around 40 years, I would say, was SAS.
But we're moving away from that. And that's actually the whole purpose of my job is to move
to a more modern language, which is R. But because of that, that's why I built up my section,
because we can't just say, oh, we want to do R now, which we are doing it. But infrastructure
and software needs to be built up. And that's what I did in my office. I built up the capability.
So now we're fully into R. And if history is to teach us anything, the previous language was
SAS, now R. So we're here to stay. And just to say the reason, because I also did the research
when I actually began working in my organization, I was tasked with the task,
go and research what is the best alternative language. And I did the research. And it's
actually on my source of research that we decided to go to R. Let's just say the only two contesters
that really came into play was R and Python. But R won it overall. But I see Python bidding in the
mix. But I say, let's just deal with one language, please. When you deal with official statistics,
the methodological consistency is very, very important. Just say, as an example, we have
vital statistics that's actually a time series that goes back over 100 years. So you really
don't want to mess with the methodology. You want to keep it the same. So that's a long answer to
a short question. It was a great answer. And I see Chloe in the chat saying that Java was
also the first programming language that she learned and hasn't used it in a decade.
I feel like someone else said Java as well. We had someone else who was coming from a much more
computer science background recently, which I always really love as the sort of transition,
because I come from the statistics side, where we're all trying to get into the computer science
side perpetually and feeling like we're missing a computer science side all the time.
It's nice that there's a mix of us out there. Thank you, Anna, for asking your question.
We had an anonymous question come up here in the Slido that says, did you have any pushback
on implementing or growing the statistical analysis team? And how did you convince people
on the value of statistics? Which might not have been too hard in the literal office of
central office of statistics, but have you ever had
any pushback on implementing or growing anything in your area?
Yeah, the pushback was not major, but I guess from the very beginning,
the idea was floating there in the ether. I just sort of took the torch and I showed the value.
Okay, so if we move here, what is the value? And I think that's what I've been doing ever
since, showing the value. So show them the value, why we're doing this.
And once we began moving to it, the reason why my team grew so much,
because the management board, the senior management, well, they've seen the value.
I never asked for more people. I was always given more people say, you're doing a good thing. We
want you basically to scale. Some people say, oh, can you duplicate yourselves? Like, nope.
So therefore we'll give you more people. So it was fairly organic, but there was a little pushback
every now and then, but my strategy was always show the value, show why we're doing this.
And therefore the pushback was minimal because that's the general trend within the statistical
offices. And just to say statistical offices worldwide, they're very, very closely connected
groups. So I work with many, many other statistical offices across the globe. That's Canada
and Australia and from everywhere. We're very close group work together very, very much. So yeah.
Wonderful. Thank you, anonymous asker. That was a great question.
I wanted to remind everybody that I put a poll in the Slido. That's right. Slido does polls too.
I think that from your view, you have a slider at the top that'll show you both the Q and A
and polls. And it seems that I'm not alone because my poll was, do you answer your door readily or
do you not want anybody to knock on it? And 61, more than 60% of us have said, please don't knock
on my door. I don't want to answer it. So I feel a lot better that I'm not alone. But also I wanted
to shout out lots and lots of people talking about their first languages in college or wherever they
learned them. And it's been so interesting just seeing them filter through. Like Sundae said,
I think it was PHP first and then JavaScript. Several other people saying it was Java that
was their intro language. Some people saying it was HTML from building their custom MySpace.
Yep. That was probably me too, building GeoCities and AngelFire in the 90s. And then a few like
C++. I love C as a first language. I feel like that would have been really nice. I learned C
after R and SAS syntax. And I really, really loved it. All right. Keep telling us your very,
very first languages. I would love to know. I've only seen, I think, one which is SAS. Bill says
SAS first. Russ has got Perl first. Oh, my goodness. Okay. Let's hop on to the next question
here. I wanted to shout out Adam's question. Adam Taggart, if you would like to unmute and ask yours.
And Vitas, feel free to answer this in whatever way you would like to.
Do we have Adam? There he is. Hey, Adam. Hi, everybody. Hi, Vitas. Thanks for being here
today. You mentioned very early on that it sounded like the most recent thing you've added to your
workflow is GIS or geospatial data. And that's something which I'm I wasn't originally trained
in, but I've just spent the last three years doing. And now I'm wondering how you're incorporating
that into the statistics and the data that you were already processing. Can you give us a case
example of how you might put in? You mentioned CO2. So I'm assuming you're getting that from
something like the ERA5 system or Copernicus and creaking it in and then applying it to
areas of Ireland. Yeah. So I suppose like just to make this claim, I manage analytics platform
that does statistics. Now, the GIS has become so big that it's entire different section that
got set up within the methodology division. And actually, the person that is leading that
section sits right across from me, and he just left. So I guess what I'm
saying that the area is so big, I don't deal with it, but I would need to deal with it indirectly
because I manage the statistical platform. And you know what happens, people say, you know,
it's very compute intensive, so I need to process it. But because it's becoming such impactful thing,
entire new section is now made. And a lot of it is too complicated for me. I understand
at the high level, but the things that you mentioned, my colleague, Justin, he also mentioned
that Copernicus, they get the data, they try to measure it. And there's a lot of international work
that I know that my colleague here does here on the satellite data, because there's a lot of things
that you can measure from the satellite data that you cannot do otherwise. Now, my interactions,
what it would be when he wants to process large amounts of data, and if he crashes his session,
because the data moves into terabytes, that's where I come in. But it's getting bigger. It's
definitely getting bigger and bigger. And there's a lot of EU projects and UN projects just dedicated
to satellite GIS data. All right, wonderful. Thank you, Adam, for asking that amazing question.
And I realized what I should have put in as the poll, so I just fixed it, but I actually put it
in as a word cloud. Can everybody see it in the Slido? It's asking you what your first coding
language was that you learned. It's only going to let you enter one word, I think, like one word.
So yes, I see HTML in there, all in one word, or C++ together, or Sass, or yeah. Okay, I'm wondering
what will grow here. So far, Java and C++ are winning. And Basic, which I'm really surprised
about, there's Python. Okay, we can keep track of that in a minute. And I will put a little screenshot
of the final one when we get in there. Let's head back over to Slido, grab some more questions.
I see one from Nelson. It's got an asterisk, so I'll read it for you, Nelson. He says,
for the administrative data, how easy is it for other organizations to provide
the needed information? Do you share across organizations pretty well?
So yeah, that's where I suppose it gets a little bit complicated. I suppose we
are a governmental agency and work with other governmental agencies. It takes a lot of time
and relation building to acquire the data if it's within the other governmental agencies,
like it's easier. But then, like, no, we'd be trying to acquire data. I think, like, it was
a scanner receipt data is another very rich data source. But I know there's multiple
data acquisition initiatives. And we always try to make it very clear, look, we are statistical
and that will produce statistics for the greater good. We'll make it all public for the greater
good. But again, I don't deal within that area, but I know that it takes a fairly long time to
acquire. But once you acquire it, you can produce mountain of statistics. And that's where, as I
said, different data sources come in. So there's a scanner data from the shops, which is very rich
data source for things like CPI and GDP and purchase of goods. But it does take a fair
amount of time. I know that some things go on for a long time. Let's put it that way.
Let's put it that way. Okay. Well, we have a word cloud that is growing. Zach, I fixed your name in
the word cloud. And BASIC is winning so far, followed by Java, C++ and Python. Go stick your
vote in there by typing a single word. And we can see how many more people we can get. We have 44
respondents so far. And in the meantime, I will go back over to Slido. And let's grab another
question. Okay. Oh, I love this one. It's a two-parter. I'm going to ask the first part of it.
And it was, how did you find communicating the uncertainty and interpretation of statistical
analysis? The hardest part for me. Uncertainty. I suppose uncertainty. So
everything in statistics is an estimate within the confidence interval. Now, as far as I know,
we don't use confidence intervals. We just use plain statistics. So if it's a survey,
a survey is always a degree of some uncertainty. Now, I'm really going out of my depth here. But
I wouldn't want to say anymore. But yeah, we report on statistics in most of the
cases. I like to look at the high level. It's a counting exercise. The actual statistics
is actually pretty straightforward. What I would say, 90% of the job is actually preparing the
data and getting into the right format. So it's actually getting rid of that uncertainty. Is
this data good? Is this not data? Cleaning it, formatting it. Once your data is clean,
and you know these records are valid, these are not valid, this is from wrong time period,
the actual statistics is pretty straightforward. You just say, this is bigger than this one.
That's essentially what it is. So to go back to your question, I think I answered it now. So
how do you get rid of uncertainty? We spend a lot of time on data preparation. That's where
all the time lies. And that's where methodology comes in, formatting, classifications, where we
do most famous classification would be NUTS regions, which is geographical regions. And
we publish statistics on your geographical regions. And then we have, I think the newest
one is the NACE 2.2, which is a classification, let's say, on different jobs. So if we see,
there's a rise in IT or rise in this section and this section. So there's multiple tools.
And I'll mention another one, there's a GSBPM model, which covers the entire statistical model,
from how do you acquire the data to all the way how you disseminate the data. And there's a lot
of work being done there. So that's a very long-winded answer to, I'd say, a fairly heavy
question. It's a heavy question. It is. It's a really good one though. The other part was,
do you work with other governmental departments in Ireland?
Oh, yes, closely. I say they work with me because of my work that I've done with the POSIT platform.
And I think we are one of the first, a lot of them reach out to me and ask questions.
How did you do it? From high level to low level questions, I had more than a half a dozen
departments reach out to me because I've done something good and good news spread fast. So
they do reach out and they do ask, and like, what are you using and how are you using it?
So yes, I do work a lot with them. Sometimes too much, you know, you get to the point where
you become failure-prone success when too many people reach out. But I do like engaging with
people. So I almost never, never say no. I mean, same. I end up in the same boat,
fetus. Okay. We had an anonymous one that bubbled to the top. And if you are not aware,
you can upvote questions in Slido. So if you see one that you like, you can press the little
upvote button. This one has bubbled to the top and it says, which books, newsletters, and the like,
do you follow? Is there anything that you particularly like? I'll throw podcasts in
there as well, if you happen to like podcasts. So I am biggest, I suppose, user of LinkedIn.
I try to stay away as much as possible from, I suppose, like all the other social media,
but I'm trying to use LinkedIn now. On LinkedIn, I wouldn't be able to name you what I follow.
Well, I follow, you know, UN pages, all the international organizations, what they do,
because it's interesting to see where statistics is moving. So I follow, okay. I follow a lot of
other statistical agencies around the world. So I follow them. And then I follow the United
Nations, the European commission. Then within Europe, we have organization. This actually
would be very interesting. It's called Eurostat. So every country within Europe needs to submit
their statistical releases to Eurostat. And Eurostat serves as an entity that takes all
statistics from all the countries, and then they're standardized and they easily compare.
And then you could get to position that you can say GDP of Ireland is this versus compared GDP
of France, because all statistics come into Eurostat and they're compared, they're standardized.
So that's the power. So I follow them and many, many followers on LinkedIn. I really try to use
LinkedIn because it's a good place to see where things are going and also for events. So yeah.
Also for events, that's how you find out about the hangout probably.
Yeah.
Okay. So we have an in of 64 so far on Slido for our word cloud, and I posted a screenshot of it
and still basic is the winner. We have a small problem in that Slido seems to not think that our
alone, if you just type in R is anything, it's like you've typed in a single letter. What do
you want from me? Therefore we have a little bit of stratification in the R universe here. I see
tidy verse R, I see base R, I see R stats. So R may look a little less represented than it is.
There's also R programming. And that was my first one as well. I don't think I can vote
because I am the host, but you can consider me in the R category as well.
But still basic is very, very up there. I think if we combined all of the R ones together,
it would be winning because it's not showing R as a single letter as an answer,
but I can see on the background that 15 people entered R. And for some reason,
it won't let it show in the word cloud. So R is winning from behind the scenes.
All right. Let's hop back over to Slido and grab another question. And I saw one from Nelson again
that I love. Let's ask this one for him because he's got an asterisk in it. It says, do you use
non-traditional data such as sentiment analysis of social media? Short answer, no, I have not
heard being used. I have used it in college. I remember it was one of the first projects, but
no, we do not use that. I had my own personal ideas. It's an interesting source, but no,
we do not use that. We are governmental agency, extremely regulated. The statistics that we do,
as I said, we do 300 releases. We do have a thing called frontier statistics. So when
somebody says, oh, this would be a cool statistic to do, which is not part of our, let's say,
official established 300 statistics, it does become a frontier statistics on X, Y, Z. And
sometimes it becomes a new statistic that we continue on. But no, never sentiment analysis
because I could see how that would get, that actually goes back like, how do you clean your
data? How a lot of ambiguity could be built in there. And like, no, we try to focus as much as
we can on pure facts, statistics, like things that are extremely quantitative, 5.2 million people
in the country. So we try to do high, high accuracy as much as we can.
Totally, totally understandable, but a fantastic and interesting question.
You said that you had some thoughts of your own on possibilities there.
Do you have any opinions that are non-official that you'd like to share?
No, no. I guess just even from my college days, I knew that you could
subscribe to and get the entire data stream of some of these platforms. That's, you know,
I love data. I love big data. My close thing at heart is speed. How do you process big data fast?
So I know that some social media is extremely rich data source. So there's a lot of data there,
but to analyze it is very complex. So I suppose like, you know, it's just that it's a very
large volume data source, but that's just my own, my own opinions.
Wonderful. Well, I saw an anonymous question pop up here that is in the same vein. It's kind of a
follow-up and it's, do you analyze any free text data? And if so, how do you deal with the poor
data quality that is always present in free text data?
Yes, yes, we do. I think this is for job classifications. I can't exactly tell how it
comes in, but I do know it's actually one of the big use cases of machine learning and one of the
new cases of Gen2BI as well. When a job description is given, like what is your job and you describe
it, like I work with computers and servers and yada, yada, yada. What we need to do,
we need to take that free text and classify it against NACE 2.2, which is a big classification
that has a bucket for each type of job. So if I work with computers and servers and so on,
in which bucket would I go? So the only way that we can classify, say, okay, based on this
description, you go in this bucket. So yes, we do free text. And I guess for this particular use
case, that's where actually, as I said, vanilla machine learning, that's where it actually comes
in very handy. Although a lot of people now experimenting and finding that Gen2BI is actually
is actually pretty good at classifying which bucket which classification you go in based on the
description and there's a lot of use cases and even actually I think some people build thing called
Open Source Adoption in Government, Positron, Shiny, shinyapps
Very slow adoption and acquisition of Open Source tools
Took 9 months for my agency to approve Positron for use
Do you encounter the same issue? If so, how have you addressed that inertia?
Again, it's kind of easy for us that Open Source is being adopted globally
and I work a lot with UN and I go to Geneva and I know that there is a project at such a high level
that really embraces Open Source at a very, very high level
so that helps, so I suppose like you know it pushes from top down and even within my organization
Open Source is now being embraced, when I began it wasn't the case
because at the beginning when if you want to do Open Source the main question is the support
we cannot deal with something that doesn't have official support, so again I showed the value
and that's where I suppose again Posit came in, it's like we want to use Open Source but we want support
because we cannot support it ourselves but then we want flexibility of the Open Source
and that's where like all the R libraries come in and I guess also even at a lower level
we'd be using Linux, Linux is Open Source but we want support so therefore we'd use Red Hat
because they have support that's the underlying operating system that runs everything so
to answer your question I show the value again, I show the value that's what we're getting but what
helps is the buy-in from top level which is I suppose like at the UN at the lower level
these Open Sources being really embraced so it helps a lot although it wasn't there but now it's there
It takes time, I think a lot of people in the chat are saying that they have faced
similar things and this answered a question that Paul had entered as well but there was a little
bit of a follow-on in Paul's question which was how many SaaS users did you have to convert
maybe a little bit about the scale of that sort of conversion
A lot, a lot, a lot so we are now we are currently organization of 1200 people
and I would say people that you know program and use previously SaaS day-to-day would be
and this is my estimate it'd be like 500
so a lot and I am I'm estimating I say like in total have 1200 people I guess senior management
you know they don't don't really use us but day-to-day people that would be running programs
and then we'd have around 200 statisticians now statisticians this is where your like heavy
programming lies in these are the people that write all the statistical releases they come up
with methodology but after that like nowadays like you know other people as well supporting
admin functions they would also be so in total I would say around 500 now I have pushed more than
half already into the new platform and just to supplement that like for us it's a it's a five
year project and we are more than halfway through this is the biggest project for our organization
which I happen to lead and the biggest amount of elephant in the room is the code the infrastructure
is built expertise is built we're very big fans of git and our studio integrates with
git very well so that's one of the big deals again I show the value and great tool speaks
for itself you know it doesn't need advertisement like I would say like you know the git was very
very good because once people put their code on git in internal git now need to mention
internal version control yeah but I'm still a bit to go in practice you know all the
all the suppose people that love R you know they jump on it right on board like you know and once
you move closer to the end you know it's people you know there's been on holiday for a bit and
then come back it's like oh now I need to move to R so yeah I think that's a great sort of
explanation of the scope not only just with the number of 500 and about half of them converted
but also the span of time that that is you're not saying this is all going to change in six
months or a year you're saying this is a five-year endeavor and it takes a long time for things to
change and many people myself included have experienced this in organizations that are
tens of thousands of people big and have so many people to change that it that could be a 25 year
process of changing things and not not even just a five-year process so I appreciate that question
thank you thank you it's a great one um I saw a question from Arsenis in here we have about 14
minutes left just as a time check for everybody Arsenis if you could ask your question live
that'd be great I'm gonna stick it in the top here and put it in the chat sure cool thanks Libby
thanks for joining us today and chatting with us so my question comes from the perspective of a
former statistical agency employee in the U.S. and having seen what like Stats Canada does a
big difference is that the U.S. has multiple statistical agencies that put out stats,
Stats Canada has one singular agency that pretty much does everything and I'm wondering two things
first which version like what do you all do in Ireland with with that respect and with that do
you find that doing it that way is better or worse in terms of maintaining methodology and code bases
and things of that nature so I'm aware I suppose of the U.S. situation because I spoke with few
people from the U.S. and I had no idea the U.S. office was set up the way it is which is as I said
like a lot of different organizations no we don't have that problem we have a central office in
Ireland that does all of the statistics there's no there's no other offices and from my working
working with other countries exactly the same so there's a term called NSI national statistics
office of NSO sorry and like every country in Europe has it and it's always one as far as I know
I was actually speaking with a director from India I think like you know it might be a bit
different there like they're a huge country but I think it even there it's organized and
was actually interesting to see their their service size alone is half a million so the
it was very nice to see it no like it's all the same and actually going beyond that I mentioned
we even go like a level higher each country has its own statistical office but then in Luxembourg
Eurostat well they compile everything and then we can we basically have European statistics to
measure the entire statistics of Europe so I can't imagine what place we'd be in like you know
let's say if we had multiple statistical offices that's just not a thing from my experience in
Ireland or or in Europe so from methodology everything is standardized even at the format
like so how we disseminate statistics even that is fairly standard across Europe so it eliminates
a lot of potential problems that could be there but they have never arisen so it don't exist
thank you so much Arsenis for asking a great question excuse me I see a question from
Noor here that has risen to the top and it also covers a little bit of an anonymous
question so Noor I would love it if you could ask that one live hello can everyone hear me
yes yeah perfect so Vytautas as someone who is in government what are some of the unique
challenges and security limitations involved with integrating AI and other AI like systems
into your infrastructure it's extremely cautious and regulated so quality and safety is always
first so I suppose like we are proceeding very cautiously so
if I want to do AI it takes a long time to get it approved because there's so many assurances
that you need to and rightfully so I want to implement AI and I need to jump through many
hoops but to be honest I do it with pleasure because I well not with pleasure but I understand
the reason behind like you know everybody needs to be assured and we have AI governance board
within my organization that involves everybody from all over I suppose like aspects of the
organization you know HR IT infrastructure everyone so everybody wants to do AI there's
dozens and dozens of use cases but everybody's being very cautious and at the center of it being
data so it's an ongoing thing but even at the high level at the senior management level like
the language is changing like at like now everybody's aware I actually began I developed
a use case for AI which was SASTAR in 2023 which created us immense value and back then they're
like what are you using an LLM what's an LLM nobody knew back then it just came out but now
now everybody knows it again it comes back to value can you show the value why this is useful
if you can show the value useful well that helps and that's my been I suppose that's the way I
operate I show the value explicitly clearly and that gets the buying I love it I wanted to ask
too as just a quick follow-up because I can't remember if you mentioned this when we were
talking about tools do you use Shiny oh yes yes we so I suppose just to give when I built
it within my organization I called our platform so we use everything with the workbench the packet
manager and the shine now the shiny has become too popular and that's why that's why my team
have grown so much so we use it a lot we have a lot of internal apps and yeah we use it a lot a
lot there's a lot of internally facing us because when people develop shiny apps there's a skill
element because I always say like no before let's say if you're not using shiny what was the
alternative you become a full dev developer you learn like html javascript css and nobody really
knew that they were like no probably one or three people within the organization but now because we
have the connect server anyone can spin up a shiny app and it's very easy and that's where we see like
a lot of innovation and then when you combine that with ai well that's another level of capability
and it's very easy and to be honest it makes it too easy too easy I actually have to say
no to people in in some cases because we use it a lot and we have many many shiny apps it's too
easy to make a shiny app it's like really great pr and terrible pr at the same time
I am I am I'm the governing body so to say I say like you know who gets it yeah we
we actually developed we developed a shiny dashboard to show how many shiny apps we have
and I think I think it's very meta it approached three digits yeah it approached it approached
three digits okay all right I believe you then it might be a little too easy to create a shiny app
well we only have seven minutes left but there's a great question from Hubert in the Slido and I
would love it if he could ask that live Hubert let's see if we can unmute you here I'll put
your question in the chat as well okay so there he is hey I'm here hello um hello so do you have
any issues and I think you've hinted at this and some of your answers today and some of the
discussions already but if you do you have issues recoding of old data to new data standards I mean
that's a big deal in my area in cancer research to where you know state-of-the-art 20 years ago
data versus data that is now you know variables have changed categories have changed algorithms
have changed and that's part one part two do I get to ask two parts I don't know we only have six
minutes left okay I'll stop at that one do you would Hubert would you call that harmonization
yeah you can call that harmonization it's more harmonization and just the re sometimes recoding
of those fields you know because you know they may not directly compare so how do you put them
together in analysis yeah so just to say that's why the project is five years that's why the project
lasts five years because as I said before all of our statistical releases are underpinned by
code now all of this code needs to be translated when we translate the code we need to maintain
methodological consistency now we have multiple ways to address this I would say one of the
most useful ones we do parallel runs so we have a SAS and we have our writing our code we use
historical data run it at the same time produces the same results now every statistician is an
expert within in their domain and it's their responsibility to do that but we also do code
reviews on top of that where methodology quality it would come in but that is the reason why it's
taking us five years now we made a very good progress and we'll keep on moving on now I would
say in and like we we have found like you know some things were like you know I would have some
statisticians to say oh these like inconsistencies like what's inconsistency goes like well if you go
to fifth decimal place all around it like that and this is rounded like that like you know something
along those lines were like you know it actually goes very very far I goes okay like you know I
think we can we can deal with that you know so overall it's going very very well but that is
why it's taking five years so it's a parallel runs uh code reviews by other than the statistician
that owns the code because you just need somebody from outside to have a look have a sanity check
so that's that's how we do it amazing we got it in there we have four minutes left still
all right so vitas I would love to ask you the question we ask everybody which is do you have
a piece of career advice that maybe you wish that you knew before you had gotten into the
data field or that you think would be helpful for others yeah I would say like as I grew I changed
I did not remain the same as I when I began my education and I say it might seem a bit
stereotypical don't focus on the tool like you know I say like the thing that helps me the most
it's kind of like logical reasoning breaking problem down so whatever the tool is it's kind
of like you know learn how to solve problems do not shy away from a challenge because even within
my organization when I began working like you know tools change and technology changes but within the
area that I worked it's always like you know fixing a problem so logical thinking breaking down
the problem I think like that's the thing that helps me the most and in addition to that
the thing that I neglected the most when I was in college and I thought that it's not
important at all it's like I don't even want to do this module which is what I'm doing now
it's communication being able to talk to people and communicate well because you could be the
smartest person in a room but like if you cannot communicate that if you cannot explain it
like in a way you don't scale so also explaining complex matters to people that's serving me a lot
so breaking down problems irrelevant of the tool these days AI is a big thing and then
communication like a lot of it's like ah no communication come on man like you need to
have heavy skills yes you need to have heavy skills and understanding of technology but technology
changes if you look back at the history communication I don't think it's gonna go
that time soon so and that helped me the most you know that's why I went to UN meetings and
Eurostat and all these places because I said okay I think this this guy understands what he's
talking about so let me speak. Wonderful all right well with our last minute here I will say
thank you so much for everybody joining us Vitas thank you so much this was wonderful I hope you
had a good time. I did. Wonderful okay we had a few questions that we didn't get to thank you for
asking them anyway everybody your questions as always were so much fun and as a reminder
we do not have a data science hangout next week we have two weeks off for summer break I am so so
excited Isabella and I are both excited to get time off and Rachel will get some time off of
course she's not here today if you see her on LinkedIn later somewhere on the internet say
hello to her don't forget the link that we shared from Rachel earlier if you would like to
share your story about the changes that you've been able to make using posit tools Rachel is
our head of customer marketing so she's going to know a little bit more about this than I do but
I'm going to put this impact awards link in in the chat again if you clicked it earlier and you
weren't able to get in because you didn't have a google account Rachel let's let me know that
she fixed it so that you can get in there were some settings that needed to be changed so take
a look at that if you would like to be in the running for six free posit comp tickets in Houston
which is really really cool I don't know if we've ever done that before if you would like to save the
chat today in the top right corner of your chat there should be three dots that you can click
unless you were in the browser in which case it will be much harder but we try to save the chat
and share it on the discord server if you have not gotten on the discord server please please
do that and join us it's so much fun and we love to see you we will see you next week at the data
science lab however where on Tuesday we are going to be talking about data frames in Python why they
are a challenge and how narwhals can help solve some of those problems so if you're interested
in that come hang out with us you can go to pos.it slash dslab to register and Isabella just put that
in the chat all right everybody say goodbye to vitas goodbye